I was a new mother
كنت أماً جديدة
and a young rabbi
ومعلمة يهودية يافعة
in the spring of 2004
في ربيع عام 2004
and the world was in shambles.
وكان العالم يعيش حالة من الفوضى.
Maybe you remember.
ربما تتذكرون ذلك.
Every day, we heard devastating reports from the war in Iraq.
كل يوم، كنا نسمع التقارير المدمرة من الحرب في العراق.
There were waves of terror rolling across the globe.
واجتاحت موجات من الرعب العالم .
It seemed like humanity was spinning out of control.
بدا الأمر وكأن البشرية تخرج عن السيطرة.
I remember the night that I read
أذكر الليلة التي قرأت فيها
about the series of coordinated bombings
عن سلسلة من التفجيرات المنسقة
in the subway system in Madrid,
في مترو الأنفاق في مدريد،
and I got up and I walked over to the crib
فنهضت واتجهت إلى سرير الأطفال
where my six-month-old baby girl
حيث كانت ابنتي ذات الستة أشهر
lay sleeping sweetly,
نائمة بشكلٍ لطيفٍ،
and I heard the rhythm of her breath,
وسمعت إيقاع أنفاسها،
and I felt this sense of urgency coursing through my body.
وشعرت بإحساس طارئ يعبر جسدي.
We were living through a time of tectonic shifts in ideologies,
كنا نعيش في زمن من التحولات الأيديولوجية،
in politics, in religion, in populations.
في السياسة، في الدين، في السكان.
Everything felt so precarious.
كان كل شيء يبدو غير مستقر.
And I remember thinking,
وأذكر أنني كنت أفكر،
"My God, what kind of world did we bring this child into?
"يا إلهي، الى أي عالم جلبنا هذه الطفلة؟
And what was I as a mother and a religious leader
وما الذي كنت بصفتي أماً وقائدة دينية
willing to do about it?
على استعداد للقيام به بشأن ذلك؟
Of course, I knew it was clear
طبعاً، كنت أعلم أنه من الواضح
that religion would be a principle battlefield
أن الأديان ستكون ساحة المعركة الرئيسية
in this rapidly changing landscape,
في هذا المشهد المُتغيير بوتيرة سريعة،
and it was already clear
وكان من الواضح أيضاً
that religion was a significant part of the problem.
أن الدين كان جزءاً كبيراً من المشكلة.
The question for me was,
لكن السؤال بالنسبة لي هو
could religion also be part of the solution?
هل يمكن ان تكون الأديان جزءا من الحل ؟
Now, throughout history,
الآن، وعبر التاريخ،
people have committed horrible crimes and atrocities
ارتكب الناس الكثير من الجرائم والأعمال الوحشية
in the name of religion.
باسم الدين.
And as we entered the 21st century,
وبعدما أصبحنا في القرن الواحد والعشرين،
it was very clear that religious extremism was once again on the rise.
أصبح من الواضح أن التعصب الديني يزداد.
Our studies now show
تظهر دراساتنا الآن
that over the course of the past 15, 20 years,
أنه عبر السنوات 15 أو 20 الأخيرة،
hostilities and religion-related violence
الأعمال العدائية والجرائم المرتبطة بالدين
have been on the increase all over the world.
ازدادت حول العالم أجمع.
But we don't even need the studies to prove it,
ولسنا بحاجة لدراسة لنثبت ذلك،
because I ask you, how many of us are surprised today
لأنني سألتكم كم منا تفاجئ اليوم
when we hear the stories of a bombing or a shooting,
عند سماع قصص عن إطلاق النار أو الإنفجارات،
when we later find out that the last word that was uttered
عندما نكتشف بأن أخر كلمة لفظت
before the trigger is pulled or the bomb is detonated
قبل إطلاق الزناد أو انفجار القنبلة
is the name of God?
كانت اسم الرب؟
It barely raises an eyebrow today
بالكاد تفاجأ أحدنا اليوم
when we learn that yet another person
عندما علم بأن شخص أخر
has decided to show his love of God
قرر أن يظهر حبه للرب
by taking the lives of God's children.
بسلب حياة أولاد الرب.
In America, religious extremism
في أمريكا، التطرف الديني
looks like a white, antiabortion Christian extremist
يبدو كمسيحي متطرف ضد الإجهاض
walking into Planned Parenthood in Colorado Springs
يتجه نحو منظمة تنظيم الأسرة في كورولادو سبرنغ
and murdering three people.
ويقتل ثلاثة أشخاص.
It also looks like a couple
يبدوان كشخصين
inspired by the Islamic State
متأثران بالدولة الإسلامية
walking into an office party in San Bernardino and killing 14.
يدخلان الى حفلة للحزب في سان بيدرنادو ويقتلان 14 شخصا.
And even when religion-related extremism does not lead to violence,
حتى وإن كان التعصب الديني لا يقود إلى العنف،
it is still used as a political wedge issue,
فهو لا يزال يستخدم كقضية سياسية،
cynically leading people to justify the subordination of women,
ويقود الناس لتقليل من شأن المرأة بشكل ساخر،
the stigmatization of LGBT people,
وإلحاق العار بمجتمع المثليين،
racism, Islamophobia and anti-Semitism.
العنصرية والإسلاموفوبيا ومعاداة السامية.
This ought to concern deeply
هذا ما يجب علينا الاهتمام به بشدّة
those of us who care about the future of religion
هؤلاء الذين يهتمون بمستقبل الأديان
and the future of faith.
ومستقبل الإيمان.
We need to call this what it is:
علينا أن نسمي هذا بمسماه الحقيقي:
a great failure of religion.
الفشل الكبير للأديان.
But the thing is, this isn't even the only challenge that religion faces today.
لكن في الحقيقية، هذا ليس التحدي الحقيقي الذي تواجهه الأديان هذه الأيام.
At the very same time
في نفس الوقت
that we need religion to be a strong force against extremism,
الذي نحتاج فيه للدين لنكون قوة تواجه التعصب،
it is suffering from a second pernicious trend,
فهي تعاني من توجّه خبيث آخر،
what I call religious routine-ism.
ما أسميه حركة التضامن الدينية.
This is when our institutions and our leaders
هنا حيث تكون مؤسساتنا وقيادينا
are stuck in a paradigm that is rote and perfunctory,
عالقة في نموذج روتيني حفظوه عن ظهر قلب،
devoid of life, devoid of vision
خال من الحياة ، خال من الرؤيا
and devoid of soul.
وبدون روح.
Let me explain what I mean like this.
دعوني أوضح ما أعنيه بهذا.
One of the great blessings of being a rabbi
أحد أفضل الهبات لكونك حاخاما
is standing under the chuppah, under the wedding canopy, with a couple,
هي الوقوف تحت الشوباه، تحت قبة الزفاف، مع زوجين
and helping them proclaim publicly
وإعلان حبهما على الملإ
and make holy the love that they found for one another.
وتقديس الحب الذي جعلهما يجدان بعضهما.
I want to ask you now, though,
أريد أن أسألكم الآن،
to think maybe from your own experience
لتفكروا من خلال تجربتكم
or maybe just imagine it
أو ربما تخيلوا
about the difference between the intensity of the experience
الفرق بين التجربة المكثفة
under the wedding canopy,
تحت مظلة الزفاف،
and maybe the experience of the sixth or seventh anniversary.
أو ربما التجربة عند الاحتفال بالذكرى السادسة أو السابعة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And if you're lucky enough to make it 16 or 17 years,
أو ربما اذا كنت محظوظاً كفاية تحتفل بالذكرى 16 أو 17،
if you're like most people, you probably wake up in the morning
إذا كنت كأغلب الناس، ربما ستستيقظ في الصباح
realizing that you forgot to make a reservation at your favorite restaurant
وتتذكر أنك نسيت القيام بحجز في مطعمك المفضل
and you forgot so much as a card,
ونسيت حتى البطاقة،
and then you just hope and pray that your partner also forgot.
وعندها تتمنى أن يكون شريكك قد نسي أيضاً.
Well, religious ritual and rites
حسناً، الطقوس الدينية والشعائر
were essentially designed to serve the function of the anniversary,
صُممت أساساً لتخدم الذكرى السنوية،
to be a container in which we would hold on to the remnants
وأن تكون وعاء نحتفظ فيه ببقايا
of that sacred, revelatory encounter
ذلك اللقاء المقدس والروحي
that birthed the religion in the first place.
الذي يعدّ مولد الأديان في المقام الأول.
The problem is that after a few centuries,
والمشكلة أنه بعد عدة قرون،
the date remains on the calendar,
بقي الوقت على الروزنامة،
but the love affair is long dead.
ولكن الحب مات منذ وقت طويل.
That's when we find ourselves in endless, mindless repetitions
وذلك عندما نجد أنفسنا في تكرار لانهائي وبلا معنى
of words that don't mean anything to us,
للكلمات التي لم تعد تعني لنا شيئا،
rising and being seated because someone has asked us to,
الوقوف والجلوس على كرسي لأن أحدهم طلب منا ذلك،
holding onto jealously guarded doctrine
والتمسك بالعقيدة بتعصب
that's completely and wildly out of step with our contemporary reality,
هذا أمر خارج عن واقعنا المعاصر بشكل كامل وعشوائي،
engaging in perfunctory practice
نستمر بالقيام بالممارسات الروتينية
simply because that's the way things have always been done.
ببساطة لأن هذا هو ما نقوم به دائماً.
Religion is waning in the United States.
يشهد الدين تراجعا في الولايات المتحدة.
Across the board, churches and synagogues and mosques
سواء عبر المجالس والكنائس والمعابد والمساجد
are all complaining
جميعهم يتذمرون
about how hard it is to maintain relevance
حول صعوبة الاحتفاظ بأهميتها
for a generation of young people who seem completely uninterested,
لأجيال من الشباب غير المهتمين بها،
not only in the institutions that stand at the heart of our traditions
ليس فقط في المؤسسات الموجودة في قلب تقاليدنا
but even in religion itself.
لكن حتى في الدين نفسه.
And what they need to understand
وما عليهم أن يفهموه أنه
is that there is today a generation of people
يوجد اليوم أجيال من الناس
who are as disgusted by the violence of religious extremism
مستاؤون من عنف المتطرفين الدينين
as they are turned off
كما يحصل
by the lifelessness of religious routine-ism.
بسبب لامبالاة حركة التضامن الدينية.
Of course there is a bright spot to this story.
بالتأكيد يوجد بصيص من الأمل في كل هذا.
Given the crisis of these two concurrent trends in religious life,
مع الأزمات المتزامنة لهذين الاتجاهين في الحياة الدينية،
about 12 or 13 years ago, I set out to try to determine
منذ 12 أو 13 سنة، جلست وفكرت في محاولة لتحديد
if there was any way
إذا كان هناك أي طريقة
that I could reclaim the heart of my own Jewish tradition,
استطع من خلالها استعادة تقاليدي الدينية اليهودية الأصيلة،
to help make it meaningful and purposeful again
لجعلها مجدداً ذات معنى ولها هدف
in a world on fire.
في عالم مشتعل.
I started to wonder,
بدأت بالتسائل،
what if we could harness some of the great minds of our generation
ماذا لو استطعنا تسخير أحد أكبر العقول في جيلنا
and think in a bold and robust and imaginative way again
والتفكيرمجدداً بطريقة مبتكرة وجريئة وخيالية
about what the next iteration of religious life would look like?
حول الشكل التالي الذي ستأخذه الحياة الدينية؟
Now, we had no money, no space, no game plan,
الآن، ليس لدينا مال أو مساحة أو مخطط للعمل،
but we did have email.
لكن لدينا البريد الالكتروني.
So my friend Melissa and I sat down and we wrote an email
لذلك جلست مع صديقتي ميليسا وكتبنا رسالة إلكترونية
which we sent out to a few friends and colleagues.
أرسلناها لعدة أصدقاء وزملاء في العمل.
It basically said this:
وما يلي محتواها :
"Before you bail on religion,
"قبل أن تهاجم الدين،
why don't we come together this Friday night
لما لا نجتمع مساء هذه الجمعة
and see what we might make of our own Jewish inheritance?"
ونرى ما يمكن أن نقوم به بشأن مراثنا اليهودي؟"
We hoped maybe 20 people would show up.
كنا نـأمل أن يأتي حوالي 20 شخص.
It turned out 135 people came.
وفي الحقيقة أتى 135 شخص.
They were cynics and seekers,
كانوا ساخرين وباحثين،
atheists and rabbis.
وملحدين وحاخامات.
Many people said that night that it was the first time
قال العديد من الناس بأنها المرة الأولى
that they had a meaningful religious experience in their entire lives.
التي يخوضون فيها تجربة دينية ذات معنى خلال حياتهم.
And so I set out to do the only rational thing
وجلست للقيام بالأمرالمنطقي الوحيد
that someone would do in such a circumstance:
الذي يمكن أن يقوم به شخص ما في حياته:
I quit my job and tried to build this audacious dream,
تركت عملي وحاولت تحقيق هذا الحلم الجريء،
a reinvented, rethought religious life
وضع الحياة الدينية وإعادة النظر فيها
which we called "IKAR,"
والتي سندعوها "أيكارا"،
which means "the essence" or "the heart of the matter."
والتي تعني " الجوهر" أو "قلب الشيء".
Now, IKAR is not alone
ليست أيكارا وحيدة
out there in the religious landscape today.
في المشهد الديني اليوم.
There are Jewish and Christian and Muslim and Catholic religious leaders,
هناك زعماء دينيون مسحيون ويهود ومسلمون وكاثولكيون،
many of them women, by the way,
أغلبهم من النساء، على فكرة،
who have set out to reclaim the heart of our traditions,
شرعوا في العمل على استعادة تقاليدنا الدينية الأصيلة،
who firmly believe that now is the time for religion to be part of the solution.
ويملكون إيمانا راسخا بأنه يجب على الدين أن يكون جزءاً من الحل.
We are going back into our sacred traditions
وسنعود الى تقاليدنا المقدسة
and recognizing that all of our traditions
وندرك بأن جميع تقاليدنا
contain the raw material to justify violence and extremism,
تشمل مادة خام لتبرير العنف الديني والتعصب،
and also contain the raw material to justify compassion,
وأيضاً تحتوي مادة خام لتبرير التعاطف،
coexistence and kindness --
والتعايش واللطف--
that when others choose to read our texts as directives for hate and vengeance,
عندها يقرر آخرون قراءة نصوصنا كتوجيهات للكراهية والقتل،
we can choose to read those same texts
نقرر قراءة نفس النصوص
as directives for love and for forgiveness.
كتكريس للحب والتسامح.
I have found now
وجدت الآن
in communities as varied as Jewish indie start-ups on the coasts
في المجتمعات المتنوعة مثل اليهود على السواحل
to a woman's mosque,
والنساء المسلمات،
to black churches in New York and in North Carolina,
والكنائس الخاصة بالسود في نيويورك ونورث كارولينا،
to a holy bus loaded with nuns
والحافلات التي تستقلها الراهبات
that traverses this country with a message of justice and peace,
تعبر أنحاء هذه البلاد حاملين معهن رسالة العدل والسلام،
that there is a shared religious ethos
وتوجد بينهن روح دينية مشتركة
that is now emerging in the form of revitalized religion in this country.
بدأت تظهر على شكل بعثة دينية جديدة في هذا البلد.
And while the theologies and the practices vary very much
بينما تختلف تلك اللاهوتية والممارسات كثيراً
between these independent communities,
بين تلك المجتمعات المستقلة،
what we can see are some common, consistent threads between them.
يمكننا أن نرى المواضيع المشتركة بينها
I'm going to share with you four of those commitments now.
وسأشارككم أربع من تلك الالتزامات.
The first is wakefulness.
الأول هو اليقظة.
We live in a time today
نحن نعيش اليوم في زمن
in which we have unprecedented access
يكون فيه لدينا فرصة غير مسبوقة للحصول
to information about every global tragedy
على معلومات حول المآسي العالمية
that happens on every corner of this Earth.
التي تحدث في كل زاوية من هذه الكرة الأرضية.
Within 12 hours, 20 million people
خلال 12 ساعة، رأى عشرون مليون شخص
saw that image of Aylan Kurdi's little body
صورة أيلان الطفل الكردي الصغير
washed up on the Turkish shore.
الذي جرفته الأمواج على الشواطىء التركية.
We all saw this picture.
جميعنا رأينا هذه الصورة.
We saw this picture of a five-year-old child
رأينا هذه الصورة لطفل في الخامسة من عمره
pulled out of the rubble of his building in Aleppo.
يسحبونه من تحت أنقاض منزله في حلب.
And once we see these images,
وعندما رأينا تلك الصور،
we are called to a certain kind of action.
جميعنا نادينا بضرورة القيام بتحرك معين.
My tradition tells a story of a traveler who is walking down a road
تروي تقاليدي قصة مسافر كان يسير في الطريق
when he sees a beautiful house on fire,
عندما رأى منزل جميلا يحترق،
and he says, "How can it be that something so beautiful would burn,
وقال في نفسه "كيف يمكن لشيء بهذا الجمال أن يحترق،
and nobody seems to even care?"
ويبدو أن لا أحد يهتم؟"
So too we learn that our world is on fire,
وأدركنا أن عالمنا يحترق،
and it is our job to keep our hearts and our eyes open,
ومهمتنا الحفاظ على قلوبنا وعيوننا مفتوحة،
and to recognize that it's our responsibility
وأن ندرك بأن مسؤوليتنا
to help put out the flames.
المساعدة في إخماد النار.
This is extremely difficult to do.
وهذا شيء من الصعب جداً القيام به.
Psychologists tell us that the more we learn about what's broken in our world,
يخبرنا علماء النفس أنه عندما نعرف الأشياء المكسورة في عالمنا،
the less likely we are to do anything.
سيصبح احتمال قيامنا بأي شيء أقل.
It's called psychic numbing.
يطلق على ذلك اسم الذهول النفسي.
We just shut down at a certain point.
نحن نتراجع في لحظة معينة.
Well, somewhere along the way, our religious leaders forgot
حسناً، عند مرحلة ما، نسي قادة الدين لدينا
that it's our job to make people uncomfortable.
أن مهمتنا جعل الناس يشعرون بعدم الإرتياح.
It's our job to wake people up,
مهتنا إيقاظ الناس،
to pull them out of their apathy
وسحبهم من اللامبالاة
and into the anguish,
الى الكرب،
and to insist that we do what we don't want to do
والإصرار على القيام بما لا نريد القيام به
and see what we do not want to see.
ورؤية ما لا نريد رؤيته.
Because we know that social change only happens --
لأننا نعرف أن التغيير الإجتماعي لا يحدث إلاّ --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
when we are awake enough to see that the house is on fire.
عندما ندرك بشكل كافي أن المنزل يحترق.
The second principle is hope,
المبدأ الثاني هو الأمل،
and I want to say this about hope.
وأريد أن أقول هذا عن الأمل.
Hope is not naive,
الأمل ليس أمرا ساذجا،
and hope is not an opiate.
والأمل ليس مخدرا.
Hope may be the single greatest act of defiance
الأمل قد يكون التصرف العظيم الوحيد لتحدي
against a politics of pessimism
سياسات تشاؤمية
and against a culture of despair.
وتحدي ثقافة اليأس.
Because what hope does for us
لأن ما يقدمه الأمل لنا
is it lifts us out of the container
يساعدنا على الخروج من الصندوق
that holds us and constrains us from the outside,
الذي يحجزنا ويمنعنا من الخروج.
and says, "You can dream and think expansively again.
ويقول: "تستطيع أن تحلم وتفكر مرة أخرى على نطاق أوسع.
That they cannot control in you."
لا يستطيعون التحكم بك."
I saw hope made manifest in an African-American church
رأيت الأمل يتجسد في كنيسة أفريقية أمريكية
in the South Side of Chicago this summer,
في جنوب شيكاغو هذا الصيف،
where I brought my little girl,
أين اصطحبت ابنتي الصغيرة،
who is now 13
تبلغ الآن 13 من العمر
and a few inches taller than me,
وأطول مني بعدة انشات،
to hear my friend Rev. Otis Moss preach.
لكي تسمع موعظة القس ريف أوتس.
That summer, there had already been 3,000 people shot
في ذلك الصيف، تعرض 3000 شخصأ إلى إطلاق النار
between January and July in Chicago.
بين يناير ويوليو في شيكاغو.
We went into that church and heard Rev. Moss preach,
ذهبنا الى تلك الكنيسة واستمعنا إلى القس ريفو موس
and after he did,
وبعدما أكمل موعضته،
this choir of gorgeous women, 100 women strong,
وقفت جوقة من النساء الرائعات، جوقة تتكون من 100 امرأة قوية،
stood up and began to sing.
وبدأن بالغناء.
"I need you. You need me.
"أحتاجك ، وتحتاجني.
I love you. I need you to survive."
أحبك ، أحتاجك للنجاة."
And I realized in that moment
وأدركت في تلك اللحظة
that this is what religion is supposed to be about.
أن هذا هو فحوى الأديان.
It's supposed to be about giving people back a sense of purpose,
من المفترض أن يتمحور حول إعطاء الناس شعورا بوجود هدف،
a sense of hope,
شعورا بالأمل،
a sense that they and their dreams fundamentally matter in this world
شعورا بأن أحلامهم مهمة بالأساس في هذا العالم
that tells them that they don't matter at all.
الذي يخبرهم بأنهم غير مهمين على الإطلاق.
The third principle is the principle of mightiness.
المبدأ الثالث هو مبدأ العظمة.
There's a rabbinic tradition that we are to walk around
هناك تقليد رباني بأننا نمشي في هذا العالم
with two slips of paper in our pockets.
مع قصاصتي ورق في جيوبنا.
One says, "I am but dust and ashes."
البعض يقول " أنا مجرد غبار ورماد."
It's not all about me.
لا يتعلق الأمر بي.
I can't control everything, and I cannot do this on my own.
لا أستطيع التحكم بكل شيء، ولا أستطيع القيام بهذا لوحدي.
The other slip of paper says, "For my sake the world was created."
والقطعة الثانية من الورق تقول "لأجلي صنع العالم."
Which is to say it's true that I can't do everything,
ويمكن القول بأنه صحيح لا أستطيع القيام بكل شيء.
but I can surely do something.
لكنني بالتأكيد أستطيع القيام بشيء ما.
I can forgive.
أستطيع المسامحة.
I can love.
أستطيع الحب.
I can show up.
أستطيع أن أظهر.
I can protest.
وأستطيع أن أتظاهر.
I can be a part of this conversation.
وأستطيع أن أكون جزءا من هذه المحادثة.
We even now have a religious ritual,
لدينا الآن شعائر دينية،
a posture,
وموقف،
that holds the paradox between powerlessness and power.
تحمل بين طياتها مفارقة بين العجز والقوة.
In the Jewish community,
في المجتمع اليهودي،
the only time of year that we prostrate fully to the ground
المرة الوحيدة في السنة التي نسجد فيها كليا على الأرض
is during the high holy days.
هي خلال الأيام المقدسة.
It's a sign of total submission.
وهي دليل على الطاعة الكلية.
Now in our community, when we get up off the ground,
والأن في مجتمعنا، عندما ننهض من على الأرض،
we stand with our hands raised to the heavens,
نمسك بأيدي بعضنا ونرفعها للسماء،
and we say, "I am strong, I am mighty, and I am worthy.
ونقول: "أنا قوي وعظيم وجدير بذلك.
I can't do everything, but I can do something."
لا أستطيع القيام بكل شيء لكن أستطيع القيام بشيء ما."
In a world that conspires to make us believe that we are invisible
في عالم يتآمر ضدنا ويجعلنا نعتقد بأننا غير مرئيين
and that we are impotent,
وأننا ضعفاء،
religious communities and religious ritual
يمكن للمجتمعات والشعائر الدينية
can remind us that for whatever amount of time we have here on this Earth,
أن تذكرنا أن الوقت الذي نقضيه على الارض،
whatever gifts and blessings we were given,
أي من الهدايا والنعم التي نحصل عليها،
whatever resources we have,
وأي من المصادر التي نملكها،
we can and we must use them
نستطيع استعمالها وينغي علينا ذلك،
to try to make the world a little bit more just
لكي نحاول أن نجعل العالم أكثر بقليل
and a little bit more loving.
ولو حتى بقليل تسوده المحبة.
The fourth and final is interconnectedness.
المبدأ الرابع والأخير هو الترابط.
A few years ago, there was a man walking on the beach in Alaska,
منذ عدة سنوات كان هناك شخص يمشي على شواطىء ألاسكا،
when he came across a soccer ball
عندما رأى كرة قدم
that had some Japanese letters written on it.
كُتب عليها عبارات يابانية.
He took a picture of it and posted it up on social media,
التقط صورة لها وقام بتحميلها على وسائل التواصل الاجتماعي
and a Japanese teenager contacted him.
وتواصل معه مراهق ياباني.
He had lost everything in the tsunami that devastated his country,
فقد كل شيء في كارثة التسونامي التي ضربت البلاد،
but he was able to retrieve that soccer ball
لكنه كان قادرا على استعادة كرة القدم تلك
after it had floated all the way across the Pacific.
بعدما طفت عبر المحيط الهادىء.
How small our world has become.
كم أصبح عالمنا صغير.
It's so hard for us to remember how interconnected we all are
ومن الصعب أن نتذكر مدى ترابطنا
as human beings.
كبشر.
And yet, we know
مع ذلك، نعرف
that it is systems of oppression
بأنه نظام للإضهاد والقمع
that benefit the most from the lie of radical individualism.
يستفيد من النزعة الفردية المتطرفة.
Let me tell you how this works.
دعوني أخبركم كيف يعمل هذا.
I'm not supposed to care
من المفترض أن لا أهتم
when black youth are harassed by police,
عندما يتم اضطهاد الشباب السود من قبل الشرطة،
because my white-looking Jewish kids
لأن أولادي البيض اليهود
probably won't ever get pulled over for the crime of driving while black.
لن يتم اضطهادهم من قبل الشرطة بتهمة القيادة.
Well, not so, because this is also my problem.
حسنا، الأمر ليس كذلك، لأنها تعتبر مشكلتي أيضا.
And guess what? Transphobia and Islamophobia
واحزروا ماذا؟ يعد الخوف من الإسلام والمتحولين جنسياً
and racism of all forms, those are also all of our problems.
والتعصب بجميع أشكاله من مشاكلنا.
And so too is anti-Semitism all of our problems.
كما أن معاداة السامية تعد من مشاكلنا.
Because Emma Lazarus was right.
لأن إيما لازرس كانت محقة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Emma Lazarus was right when she said until all of us are free,
إيما لازرس كانت محقة عندما قالت "اذا لم نتحرر كلنا
we are none of us free.
لا يوجد أحد حر بيننا."
We are all in this together.
نحن جميعهاً معاً في هذا.
And now somewhere at the intersection of these four trends,
والأن عندما تتقاطع هذه الاتجاهات الأربعة،
of wakefulness and hope and mightiness and interconnectedness,
اليقظة والأمل والعظمة والترابط،
there is a burgeoning, multifaith justice movement in this country
هناك حركة مزدهرة متعددة الأديان تسعى لتحقيق العدالة في هذا البلد
that is staking a claim on a countertrend,
تستند على المطالب في الاتجاه المعاكس،
saying that religion can and must be a force for good in the world.
تقول أنه يمكن للدين يمكن أن يكون قوة للخير في العالم وعليه أن يكون كذلك.
Our hearts hurt from the failed religion of extremism,
تألمنا قلوبنا جراء فشل الدين المتطرف،
and we deserve more than the failed religion of routine-ism.
ونستحق أكثر من فشل المذهب الروتيني.
It is time for religious leaders and religious communities
لقد حان الوقت للقادة الدينيين وقادة الطوائف الدينية
to take the lead in the spiritual and cultural shift
أخذ زمام المبادرة في التحول الروحي والثقافي
that this country and the world so desperately needs --
الذي يحتاجه هذا البلد والعالم بشدة --
a shift toward love,
تحول نحو الحب،
toward justice, toward equality and toward dignity for all.
نحو العدالة ونحو المساواة ونحو الكرامة للجميع.
I believe that our children deserve no less than that.
أعتقد ان أطفالنا لا يستحقون أقل من ذلك.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)